<?xml version="1.0" encoding="ISO-8859-1"?>
<!DOCTYPE section PUBLIC "-//OASIS//DTD DocBook XML V4.4//EN"
"http://www.oasis-open.org/docbook/xml/4.4/docbookx.dtd">
<section xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude">
<title>Creating an Index</title>

  <para>
   An index is automatically generated if some index entries (<sgmltag>indexterm</sgmltag>), telling the terms to put in the index, are written in the document. The <sgmltag>keyword</sgmltag> elements are not printed but are also added to the index.
  </para>
<example><title>Index Entry</title>
  <programlisting>
<![CDATA[<para>In this paragraph is described the function 
<function>strcpy</function><indexterm><primary>strcpy</primary></indexterm>.
</para>
]]>  </programlisting>
</example>
  <para>
   The index is put at the end of the document. It is not possible to put it somewhere else.
  </para>

<section><title>Internationalized Indexes</title>

<para>The tool used by default to build the index is
<command>makeindex</command> that works fine for latin charset but it is not
suited for other charsets and UTF-8 encoding. Moreover its sorting rule is
not suited for many languages.</para>

<para>Therefore dblatex gives the possibility to use
<command>xindy</command> that allows internationalized indexing. When xindy
is used, the sorting language used is deduced from the Docbook document lang.
If the document lang has no correspondance for xindy, or if you want to force
the use of a specific sorting language, you can specify the sorting language
to use. With Xindy you can
also provide your own sort rules, but see the official Xindy documentation
for more details.</para>

<para>The following parameters are provided to use xindy and configure it:
<itemizedlist>
<listitem><para><parameter>latex.index.tool</parameter>=xindy tells dblatex 
to use xindy instead of makeindex (default).</para>
</listitem>
<listitem><para><parameter>latex.index.language</parameter> specifies the
language used to sort the indexes. Currently this parameter is relevant
only for xindy. The language set must be known by xindy (see the xindy
documentation). When not set (or empty) the sorting language to apply
is deduced from the document lang.</para>
</listitem>
</itemizedlist>
</para>
</section>
</section>
